<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Lectures in Intellectual History</title>
<link>https://www.intellectualhistory.net</link>
<language>en-gb</language>
<copyright>&#x2117; &amp; &#xA9; 2010-17. Lectures are not to be cited without permission of the author.</copyright>
<itunes:subtitle>Recordings from the popular public lecture series. From 2014 held at the University of St Andrews, and between 2010 and 2013 held at the University of Sussex.</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:author>Institute of Intellectual History, University of St Andrews</itunes:author>
<itunes:summary>Recordings from the popular public lecture series on intellectual history in all its forms and across all ages. From 2014 held at the University of St Andrews, and between 2010 and 2013 held at the University of Sussex.</itunes:summary>
<description>Recordings from the popular public lecture series on intellectual history in all its forms and across all ages. From 2014 held at the University of St Andrews, and between 2010 and 2013 held at the University of Sussex.</description>
<itunes:owner>
<itunes:name>Kris Grint</itunes:name>
<itunes:email>krisgrint@gmail.com</itunes:email>
</itunes:owner>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<itunes:category text="Society &amp; Culture">
<itunes:category text="History"/>
</itunes:category>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
<atom:link href="https://standrewsiih.github.io/lectures.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<<<<<<< HEAD
=======

<item>
<title>Cosmology and Ritual Magic in the Late Middle Ages</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Sophie Page (UCL) on the rich diversity of cosmological thinking during the Middle Ages</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>The importance of general celestial influences on the Earth in Aristotle's cosmological model enabled the art of astrology to find a large degree of acceptance in intellectual circles by the mid-twelfth century, even if throughout the late Middle Ages it continued to be haunted by the debate about determinism. Astrology - or the study of the movements and relative positions of celestial bodies in order to make predictions about human personalities, dispositions, and public and personal events - included the belief that the planets could incline men to good and evil, and negatively influence the course of events. In this paper, Sophie Page examines how the question of whether or how demons could provoke, manipulate or make use of these celestial influences was of particular concern to three different types of medieval author: theologians explaining the structure and operations of the cosmos, authors of literary or popular scientific texts discussing the origins of evil in the world, and writers of texts on astrology and magic, whose main goal was to identify networks of power in the cosmos which could be manipulated by humans.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-10-sophie-page.mp3" length="53430276" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-10-sophie-page.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>56:54</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>
>>>>>>> master

<item>
<title>Natural law and casuistic reasoning in Roman jurisprudence</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Caroline Humfress (St Andrews) on the different ways of dealing with casuistry in Roman jurisprudence</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>There is no evidence for any Roman jurist writing a treatise entitled On Natural Law, or similar. Ius naturale had a very limited place in Roman jurisprudence, and when Roman jurists want to reason about law, they pretty much always began from the standpoint of the Roman ius civile and worked outwards. There is a fundamental difference between this concentric way of reasoning about natural law, and the way in which the medieval natural lawyers influenced by Thomas Aquinas, as well as later 17th and 18th century thinkers, reason about it. In this lecture, Caroline Humfress examines this tension.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-09-caroline-humfress.mp3" length="53522823" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-09-caroline-humfress.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>57:32</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Wordsworth’s “Sonnets Dedicated to Liberty” (1802-3) and the British Revolutionary Past</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Phil Connell (Cambridge) on the distinctive ideological context of William Wordworth's “Sonnets Dedicated to Liberty”</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>William Wordworth's Sonnets Dedicated To Liberty are dominated by his personal and political connections with France, and his changing attitudes to Britain's participation in the counter-Revolutionary war effort. Wordsworth's experiments with the sonnet form in this period were clearly sustained, intensive and closely engaged with affairs of state. However, a number of the sonnets are also keenly responsive to 17th-century British history in ways that raise distinct challenges to our sense of Wordworth's shifting political attitudes. Are the sonnets continuous with Wordsworth's early radicalism? Or are the poems better understood as a redirection of political and imaginative energies under the pressure of the Napoleonic threat towards the conservative defence of the nation and tradition? In this lecture, Phil Connell considers these and other questions.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-08-phil-connell.mp3" length="46784417" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-08-phil-connell.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 4 Apr 2017 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>50:06</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Just War Doctrine in Ancient Egypt</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Rory Cox (St Andrews) on the ancient Egyptian origins of the Just War doctrine</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>In the literature of the Just War tradition there is an overdrawn association between the Just War tradition and Christian political theology. This produces a misconception that Just War is an exclusively Christian idea, and also that is an exclusively Western idea as well. In this lecture, Rory Cox argues that ideas analogous to Just War developed in Ancient Egypt, more than 2,000 years prior to the advent of Christianity and beyond the traditional boundaries of the West.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-07-rory-cox.mp3" length="44459405" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-07-rory-cox.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>47:50</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>How to do intellectual history</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor David D’Avray (UCL) on the theory and practice of intellectual history</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>How can you combine the so-called Cambridge School of intellectual history, which tends to shrink the focus to a particular period and particular context, with a longue durée approach which follows through themes over many centuries? In this lecture, David D’Avray attempts to resolve this argument with the help of 20th century German philosophers Niklas Luhmann and Hans-Georg Gadamer.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-06-david-davray.mp3" length="50345300" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-06-david-davray.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 7 Mar 2017 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>53:54</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>George Berkeley in Livorno: Missionary Anglicanism and Commerce</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Tom Jones (St Andrews) analyses the importance of George Berkeley's visit to Livorno to his intellectual history</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Whilst George Berkeley's visit to Livorno in 1714 may seem relatively unremarkable at first look, the content of the sermons he preached there appear significant to the attitudes and behaviours of his later life. Chief among these is Berkeley's project to establish a university or college on Bermuda, and his interest in economic reform, particularly in Ireland in the 1730s. In this paper, Tom Jones identifies the early association of missionary Anglicanism and commerce as pivotal to our understanding of the history of Berkeley's later thought.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-03-tom-jones.mp3" length="44780056" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-03-tom-jones.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 7 Feb 2017 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>48:09</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Origins of Contemporary Liberal Theory Revisited</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Katrina Forrester (Queen Mary) delivers the eleventh István Host Memorial Lecture on the origins of Rawlsian liberal egalitarian theory</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>After the Second World War, political philosophy was dead. This changed in 1971 when John Rawls published his Theory of Justice, reviving philosophy and injecting it with normative foundations. Whilst this view has subsequently been subjected to several corrective arguments, they all implicitly confirm the idea that Rawls transformed political philosophy. And they also infer that Anglo-American political philosophy has been relatively static ever since. Meanwhile a second view, held by those interested in the broader history of the 20th century, holds that post-war welfarist ideology was in crisis in the 1970s, with welfarists and collectivists overthrown by various forms of liberalism. How does the view of the 1970s as a great period of re-invention in philosophy correspond to that vision of the decade as a moment of political crisis? In this lecture, Katrina Forrester explores this deep tension.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-01-katrina-forrester.mp3" length="42273616" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2017-01-katrina-forrester.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>45:37</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Hobbes, Rousseau and Democratic Politics</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Michael Sonenscher (Cambridge) delivers the tenth István Host Memorial Lecture on the distinction between sovereignty and government in the thought of Hobbes and Rousseau</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>The political thought of Jean-Jacques Rousseau is typically identified with two aspects of that of Thomas Hobbes. The first is the subject of sociability, and the similarities in their treatments of the natural state. The second is the civil state, and their joint hostility to any kind of independent religious organisation and, more broadly, any kind of factional grouping. In 1765, Rousseau’s entry on Political Economy in Diderot’s Encyclopédie was published in Geneva as a pamphlet entitled ‘The Citizen’. This title echoed Hobbes’ De Cive, and in this lecture, Michael Sonenscher discusses whether the similarity in titles indicates a broader similarity in thought.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-17-michael-sonenscher.mp3" length="46425389" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-17-michael-sonenscher.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>49:43</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Marxism and the Middle Ages</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Steve Rigby (Manchester) examines the role of medieval history in the foundation, elucidation and propagation of Marxist thought</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Marxist theory has had a massive influence on medieval economic and social history. Lots of historians, even those who are not Marxist in their politics, have in a sense been historical materialist in their analyses. Marx and Engels themselves, meanwhile, were very interested in the middle ages, in part because of its importance in understanding the transition from feudalism to capitalism. In this paper, Steve Rigby examines seven key Marxist claims that were illustrated by reference to medieval history.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-16-steve-rigby.mp3" length="46149038" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-16-steve-rigby.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>48:43</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Aristotle on the Ethics of Wealth</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Kleanthis Mantzouranis (St Andrews) discusses Aristotle's distinctions between active and passive wealth</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Aristotle's conception of wealth begins with the distinction he makes between two spheres of wealth: its possession (acquisition and keeping), and its use (giving and spending). In this paper, Kleanthis Mantzouranis explores the locations in which Aristotle discusses these two spheres in his corpus, namely in the first book of the Politics, which has been of interest to economists and economic historians, and in the fourth volume of the Nicomachean Ethics, which has been of interest to ethical philosophers.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-15-kleanthis-mantzouranis.mp3" length="41898664" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-15-kleanthis-mantzouranis.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 1 Nov 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>44:36</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The 'Family of Nations': A rhetorical figure and its ideology</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Milos Vec (Vienna) discusses the emotional power of metaphor in international law and international relations</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>The best known example in the history of international law might be the so-called domestic analogy. In natural law thinking, the rights and duties of individuals were transferred to the rights and duties behind states. But metaphors are more than analogies. If there is a family, who are the parents, and who are the children? And are the parents entitled to educate the children and, sometimes, even punish them? In this lecture, Milos Vec reconstructs critically the career and the function of the phrase the 'family of nations', and asks what implications such a metaphor has beyond concrete political arguments.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-14-milos-vec.mp3" length="62317049" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-14-milos-vec.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>1:07:58</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Moral Knowledge and the Decline of the Grotian Programme</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Aaron Garrett (Boston) discusses the theoretical ambition behind Francis Hutcheson's An Inquiry into the Original of Our Ideas of Beauty and Virtue</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>In the 17th and early 18th centuries in Britain, there were no clear divisions between what we now call moral epistemology, moral metaphysics, and normative moral theory. In this talk, Aaron Garrett argues that Francis Hutcheson, in refuting the work of Mandeville, attempted to make good on this long tradition of lumping these ideas together, and that this variant of a demonstrative moral science is both associated with the natural law tradition following from Grotius, and supportive of the ancient moralists.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-13-aaron-garrett.mp3" length="80050473" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-13-aaron-garrett.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>1:26:09</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>How to Plan a Global History of Political Thought</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Anthony Black (Dundee) plans a global history of political thought which considers both the variations of the past, and the predicaments of the present</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>What can we learn from the past, and from different traditions as they exist in the world? And how can such learning help us tackle the problems of today? In this lecture, Anthony Black asks whether, and to what extent, the histories of the West and the East are different, but complementary. Could it be that, in today's increasingly globalised (meaning Westernised) world, the West and East need each other? At a time of stress and short-sightedness, we would do well to remind ourselves of the resources and achievements of the human mind.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-12-anthony-black.mp3" length="37676171" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-12-anthony-black.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>54:10</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Republican Theorist as Royal Servant: James Harrington's Civil War</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Rachel Hammersley (Newcastle) delivers the J.H. Burns Memorial Lecture, arguing that our conventional understandings of the meaning of words like republicanism and monarchy do not match closely with those of the 17th century</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>It is generally accepted that the 17th century republican thinker James Harrington, author of The Commonwealth of Oceania, played very little part in the English civil wars of the 1640s. The one detail that is known about Harrington is that he was appointed gentleman of the bedchamber to the captured Charles I. Given the accounts of the positive relations between Harrington and the King, how is it that Harrington came to be one of the most prominent thinkers on republicanism?</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-11-rachel-hammersley.mp3" length="43914334" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-11-rachel-hammersley.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>1:03:28</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Barons' Wars, under other names: Magna Carta, Royalism, and the American Founding</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Eric Nelson (Harvard) delivers the ninth István Hont Memorial Lecture, exploring the ideological traditions of the American Revolution</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>How are we to understand the political thought of the American Revolution? One view - which is very much familiar - was that the patriots who made the Revolution were fundamentally radical Whigs whose great preoccupation was the terror of crown power and executive corruption. A rather different interpretation states that for many of the most important patriots this view was the wrong way round, and that they were rebels in favour of royal power, who wanted more monarchy rather than less, as their complaint was with the tyrannical Parliament. In this lecture, Eric Nelson assesses this second view, and shows that by the early 1770s appeals to the Whig ancient constitution had become quite rare in patriot writing, and by the end of the decade many patriots had assumed a completely different understanding of the feudal past, one pioneered by royalist historians of the 17th century, and then adopted by Scottish historians of the 18th century.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-10a-eric-nelson.mp3" length="50208960" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-10a-eric-nelson.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>51:43</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

 <item>
<title>A genealogy of liberty</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Quentin Skinner (QMUL) delivers the third J.H. Burns Memorial Lecture, in which he challenges the Western definition of individual liberty as the absence of interference</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Among contemporary political theorists in the West, the idea of individual liberty is generally defined in negative terms as absence of interference. In this lecture, Quentin Skinner argues that if the concept is instead approached genealogically, this orthodoxy begins to appear in need of qualification and perhaps abandonment. Because the concept of interference is such a complex one, there has been much dispute even within the liberal tradition about the conditions under which it may be legitimate to claim that freedom has been infringed. Skinner is chiefly concerned, however, with the many political theorists who have wished to challenge the core liberal assumption that freedom is best understood as absence of interference. Some doubt whether freedom is best defined as an absence at all, and instead attempt to connect the idea with specific patterns of moral behaviour. Other critics, meanwhile, agree that the presence of freedom is best understood as the absence of something, while arguing that freedom fundamentally consists in the absence not of acts of interference but rather of broader conditions of arbitrary domination and dependence.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-09-quentin-skinner.mp3" length="52972937" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-09-quentin-skinner.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 4 May 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>54:36</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Enlightenment Narrative in the Age of Liberal Reform: William Robertson in Hungary</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor László Kontler (Central European University) delivers the seventh István Hont Memorial Lecture on the reception of William Robertson's historical works in Hungary in the eighteenth century</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Was there a family resemblance between the 1707 Act of Union between England and Scotland and the constitutional compromise which followed the Hungarian rebellion led by Ferenc Rakoczi II against the Habsburgs between 1703 and 1711? In both cases, the settlement took into account the resilience as well as the vulnerability of the junior partner and in the longer run offered it the possibility of participating in a process of empire building and civilization. But such a union did not ensue in the Hungarian case, and a genuine age of improvement had not set in until the two decades preceding the revolution of 1848, whose defeat inaugurated yet another period of national frustration. In this lecture, Laszlo Kontler accounts for the role of the long Enlightenment in the age of reform in Hungary in the 1830s and 40s, and in particular argues that William Robertson's view of progress was tailor made to the preferences of the contemporary Hungarian public and intellectual science.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-07-laszlo-kontler.mp3" length="38612552" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-07-laszlo-kontler.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 5 Apr 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>39:38</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The contribution of the history of exegesis to the history of ideas</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Mark Elliott (St Andrews) examines the changes in the study and use of the Bible in the early Enlightenment</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>As Protestantism entered the modern world its biblical spirituality, on the one hand, inspired a puritan mission to restore the world to its paradisal integrity through trade and science, and yet on the other hand promoted an increasingly adversarial stance towards the world of politics and institutional religion. Either way, the biblical text appeared to be historical narrative with one literal sense, which mediated the divine action of a time gone by, so as to demand obedient correspondent action from God's present day covenanted partners, free from the bounds of socio-political structure as much as they could be. How did the interpretation of the Bible change in the course of the seventeenth century? How was it used to promote notions of political authority? And what relevance does this history of exegesis have for modern-day intellectual history scholarship? In this paper, Mark Elliott answers these and other questions.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-05-mark-elliott.mp3" length="56648627" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-05-mark-elliott.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 8 Mar 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>58:25</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

 <item>
<title>Liberty before neo-Roman republicanism: Haller’s restoration of political science</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Béla Kapossy (Lausanne) delivers the sixth István Hont Memorial Lecture on the political thought of Karl Ludwig von Haller</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>For many Jacobins, Rousseau was a saintly figure who provided the blueprint for society. In light of the intensity in which his political ideas were discussed, it seemed inevitable that Rousseau would bear the brunt of the anti-revolutionary backlash. In Germany and Switzerland, where perspectives on the French Revolution were marked by its propensity to export revolution beyond its borders, the first two decades of the 19th century saw an explosion of political writing. Those advocating constitutional reforms and unification were left with the task of untangling Rousseau's more cryptic or unpractical ideas about the general will, and of providing his theory of the state with a coherent and workable theory of representation. In this lecture, Béla Kapossy (Lausanne) elaborates on the German-speaking reception of Rousseau by focusing on the influential text of the self-taught Jurist Karl Ludwig von Haller, who was given the title 'anti-Rousseau'.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-02-bela-kapossy.mp3" length="55089231" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-02-bela-kapossy.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 2 Feb 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>56:48</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

 <item>
<title>The Alexander Romance and the Birth of the Ottoman Empire</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Dimitris Kastritsis (St Andrews) examines the Alexander Romance in Greek and Islamic traditions in the late 14th and 15th centuries</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>During the period that saw the creation of the classical Ottoman Empire, the Alexander of pseudo-Callisthenes functioned as a familiar if contested cultural currency. Across the boundaries of Christianity and Islam, legends about the ancient conqueror took on new relevance in light of contemporary political aspirations, which were closely intertwined with religious and social turmoil, and the ensuing eschatological expectations. In this paper, Dimitris Kastritsis examines the fate of the Alexander Romance, both Greek and Islamic, in the period that saw the Ottoman state grow in to a global empire.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-01-dimitris-kastritsis.mp3" length="54239024" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2016-01-dimitris-kastritsis.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>55:55</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Forgotten Range of Defences of Sociability: Hutcheson and Campbell on Hobbes</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Christian Maurer (Fribourg) describes how the arguments about sociability of Thomas Hobbes, Francis Hutcheson and Archibald Campbell are connected</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Most philosophers think that, as a matter of fact, most human beings live in some sort of society, but what brings human beings to live in society rather than in solitude? Do we need to invoke some sort of natural sociability to explain this fact? In De Cive, Thomas Hobbes argued that man was not a creature born fit for society, but rather made fit for society by education. But what then are the causes for us coming together? And why are many accounts of sociability so difficult to make sense of? In this lecture, Christian Maurer investigates responses to Hobbes made by two Scottish moral philosophers: the rather well-known Frances Hutcheson, and the relatively unknown Archibald Campbell.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-17-christian-maurer.mp3" length="41883844" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-17-christian-maurer.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 2 Dec 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>43:03</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Ce que nous allons devenir. Belgian national identity in eighteenth-century revolution</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Jane Judge (Edinburgh) documents the rise of a Belgian national consciousness in the course of revolutionary events between 1787 and 1790</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>In 1787 Joseph II decreed a series of administrative reforms for his Belgian provinces, essentially undoing their independence. Thus began a resistance, mounted by the estates, guilds and corporations, and then a revolution. In June 1789, Joseph had declared the Joyeuse Entrée annulled, creating a whole new branch of revolutionaries. In this lecture, Jane Judge documents the different strands of both conservative and democratic revolutionary thought which emerged in the Belgian provinces at this time, and argues that this is the first instance of people thinking of themselves as Belgian in what is modern day Belgium.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-15-jane-judge.mp3" length="47202244" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-15-jane-judge.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>48:35</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Why We Need a Global History of Political Thought</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor John Dunn (Cambridge) delivers the fifth István Hont Memorial Lecture, and discusses the pressing and not just academic need for a global history of political thought</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Political thinking anywhere in the world today, as always, is irretrievably contextual. It takes its coordinates from the setting in which it finds itself. Today that setting is ever more, and unmistakably global. Whilst human populations have never been fully insulated from each other in our epoch, all of them have for some time been undergoing a process of at best, semi-voluntary de-insulation which still appears to be accelerating. However clumsily or dishonestly it may do so, contemporary political reflection has no option but to register that de-insulation as best it can and try to judge what it means. In this lecture, John Dunn argues that we now face a pressing need for a global history of political thought, and that our need is increasingly urgent and not mainly academic, and that we must recognise it promptly and frankly and set ourselves vigorously to learn how to satisfy it better.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-14-john-dunn.mp3" length="57458078" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-14-john-dunn.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 4 Nov 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>59:16</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

 <item>
<title>The History of Dialectical History: The Case of International Law</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Ian Hunter (Queensland) delivers the second J.H. Burns Memorial Lecture, tracing the emergence of dialectical histories of international law in 1840s Germany</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>There are presently two main ways of writing the history of international law, one using the methods of dialectical philosophical history, and the other approach using the methods of contextual history and legal humanism. The central difference between these historiographies is that dialectical history treat norms as formal or ideal entities that govern the unfolding of history through their dialectical interaction with facts. Whereas contextual histories view the norms of international law as contigent historical facts, that is as products of particular treaty regimes, and hence incapable of orientating history towards any particular goal, such as a cosmopolitan legal community. In this lecture, Professor Hunter clarifies this relation by sketching an outline of the history of the dialectical history of international law, beginning with a brief discussion of the most eloquent and erudite of the modern dialectical historians, Martti Koskenniemi, before offering an account of the first emergence of dialectical histories of international law in 1840s Germany.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-13-ian-hunter.mp3" length="44197807" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-13-ian-hunter.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2015 15:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>44:53</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

 <item>
<title>Reading and Remembering: Intellectual History and the Commonplace Book in the Long Eighteenth Century</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr David Allan (St Andrews) explores the history of the commonplace book in eighteenth-century Britain</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>A commonplace book, as eighteenth-century British people generally understood the term, was a handwritten document within which memories of various kinds could be captured and reused. But what was the purpose of this mnemonic exercise, and in what context were such books created? Was there a contemporary fashion for maintaining records of this type? And what can we, as historians, do with the resulting artefacts, which survive in significant numbers? In this lecture, David Allan answers these and other questions, and demonstrates how aspects of the past experiences of literate human lives can be recovered.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-12-david-allan.mp3" length="43651028" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-12-david-allan.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>44:53</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Hume, Smith and the Science of Man in Scotland</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Nick Phillipson (Edinburgh) delivers the fourth István Hont Memorial Lecture, and revisits the foundation stones, laid by David Hume and Adam Smith, of Scotland's great contribution to Enlightenment intellectual culture: the science of man</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>It is fairly conventional now to think of the 'science of man' as possibly the signal intellectual achievement of the Enlightenment in Scotland. David Hume coined the phrase  and attached it to his Treatise of Human Nature, in which he placed the study of human nature on empirical (or experimental) foundations. On this basis Hume was to develop a powerful theory of justice, political obligation, morality, beauty, and natural religion - all of it held together as the functions of what Hume calls, in the common way, sympathy. Adam Smith was an early and acute reader of Hume's Treatise, and his theories about language, property and progress can be seen to complete the Humean project and create the science of man that Hume had promised. In time, it was to be sustained by Smith's own theory of sentiment and socialibilty, based on Humean premises, but significantly different from our own. In this lecture, Nick Phillipson challenges these reasonable inferences about Hume and Smith, and asks whether we really want to think of Hume as the author of a "projet manqué", and whether we want to think of Smith as someone who was simply tweaking Humean language?</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-11-nick-phillipson.mp3" length="60365857" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-11-nick-phillipson.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>1:02:18</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Utilitarianism, the Moral Sciences, and Political Economy: Mill-Grote-Sidgwick</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Keith Tribe gives the third István Hont Memorial Lecture, tracing the foundations of the subject of Economics at the University of Cambridge, and the important contributions of J.S. Mill, John Grote, and Henry Sidgwick</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Henry Sidgwick was already something of an enigma in Cambridge less than six years after his death, and recent interest in his work has tended to compound this by re-inventing him as a modern moral philosopher. The Moral Sciences Tripos that Sidgwick led as Knightbridge Professor from 1883 had been reshaped in 1860 by John Grote, the successor in the chair to William Whewell; and so to understand the Tripos as Sidgwick first encountered it in the 1860s we need to understand quite what Grote had in mind – and Grote himself is an important figure, having in 1862 composed a running critique of John Stuart Mill’s utilitarianism. Furthermore, until the foundation of the Economics Tripos in 1903 the teaching of political economy in Cambridge was directed almost entirely to the Moral Sciences Tripos. Alfred Marshall’s strenuous efforts to detach the teaching of economics from the Moral Sciences Tripos have tended to distort subsequent understanding of “Cambridge Economics” from Marshall, through Pigou, to Maynard Keynes. In any case, Marshall’s own economics developed from his studies of John Stuart Mill. In this lecture, Keith Tribe examines the nexus between utilitarianism, ethics and political economy, to the construction of which Mill, Grote and Sidgwick made important contributions.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-10-keith-tribe.mp3" length="15251611" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-10-keith-tribe.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>1:01:12</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Jeremy Bentham on Truth and Utility</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Philip Schofield (UCL) delivers the first J.H. Burns Memorial Lecture, and explores the problematic relationship between utility and truth in the philosophy of Jeremy Bentham</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Jeremy Bentham has two very strong commitments in his thought: one is to the principle of utility, or the greatest happiness principle, as the fundamental principle of morality; the other is to truth, as indicated, for instance, in his opposition to falsehood and fiction in the law. How, then, did Bentham view the relationship between utility and truth? Did he think that utility and truth simply coincided, and hence that falsehood necessarily led to a diminution in happiness, and conversely truth led to an increase in happiness? In this lecture, Philip Schofield resolves these questions through analysis of two bodies of material: the first consists of Bentham’s writings on religion under the heading of ‘Juggernaut’ and dating from 1811 to 1821; and the second consists of the writings on judicial evidence dating from 1803 to 1812 and which appeared in his Rationale of Judicial Evidence.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-09-philip-schofield.mp3" length="13948376" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-09-philip-schofield.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 5 May 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>55:46</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>A New Approach to the Intellectual Biography of David Hume</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr James Harris (St Andrews) critiques studies of David Hume's intellectual development</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>What kind of narrative order can be imposed on the intellectual development of David Hume, a man demonstrably interested in so many different things? The history of Hume scholarship suggests this question has been found hard to answer, not least because of the variety of Hume's concerns, but also because one of Hume's concerns was philosophy. What makes the case for Hume particularly difficult is two-fold: first, his Treatise of Human Nature speaks directly to philosophers in a way other eighteenth-century books do not. Second, philosophers since the 19th century have regarded the problems that they work on as completely different in kind to the problems Hume explored in his subsequent works, such as in the Political Discourses and in the History of England. Hume, philosophers think, was both one of us and, at the same time, very obviously not one of us. In this lecture James Harris explains how previous approaches to Hume's intellectual developments have been attempted, and argues that such approaches are largely anachronistic. In their place, he suggests a new way of viewing Hume, which relocates him in his eighteenth-century context as a man of letters.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-07-james-harris.mp3" length="10896980" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-07-james-harris.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>43:04</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Intellectual History and the Study of Historiography</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Michael Bentley (St Andrews) discusses the problematic relationship between intellectual history and the study of historiography</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>What is the nature of the relationship between intellectual history and the study of historiography, and where is this relationship going? Where might it go? Or, perhaps more importantly, where should it go? In this paper, Michael Bentley expertly navigates the foundations of intellectual history and the ways both it and the study of historiography have developed and responded to criticisms over the past century, before arguing that whilst the relationship between the two subjects is extremely important and rich, it is also a relationship that is nuanced and oblique.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-06-michael-bentley.mp3" length="14079214" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-06-michael-bentley.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>56:19</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Problem of Political Counsel in Early Modern England</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Jacqueline Rose (St Andrews) explores the unwritten rules of quasi-private political advice in early modern England</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>It's a common saying that early modern England was a personal monarchy, but this era was also a conciliar age, with a polity saturated in counsel. The persistence and prevalence of counsel rested on entrenched assumptions about the nature of good rule, and of theories of the soul and man which divided reason from will. Counsel was the reason that made imperfect human will serve the common good. It made kingship function as monarchy, not tyranny. In this paper, Jacqueline Rose dissects the dual problem of political counsel: how to approach the phenomenon historically, and how it was a problem at the time. In doing so, she demonstrates that counsel is far more interesting and complex than it has previously been seen, and that, as a discourse, it was fraught with ambiguity and tension.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-05-jacqueline-rose.mp3" length="13357507" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-05-jacqueline-rose.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 7 Apr 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>53:19</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Only Game in Town? Why did Early Modern Reformers of Natural Philosophy turn almost exclusively to the Occult to replace Scholasticism?</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor John Henry (Edinburgh) explains why the majority of would-be reformers of early modern natural philosophy incorporated various Occult notions into their systems of philosophy, and relied upon them to explain the phenomena of the physical world</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>With the decline of Scholasticism, virtually all of the would-be reformers of philosophy resorted to some kind of unexplained activity in matter. Occult qualities, or mysterious hidden forces or powers in matter or in bodies which were responsible for the actions of bodies and their interactions with others, were invoked by nearly all the new philsophers in their theories of matter or bodies. Why was the turn to the Occult so ubiquitous? In this paper, John Henry explores these and other fundamental questions of early modern natural philosophy.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-04-john-henry.mp3" length="15712367" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-04-john-henry.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>1:03:07</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Intellectual History and Women</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Sarah Hutton (Aberystwyth and St Andrews) reflects on the changes in intellectual history brought about by the advent of women's studies</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>To bring women into the purview of intellectual history is not just to shine a spotlight into dark corners to reveal women that have been overlooked. There are many more historiographical issues to be faced, not least the fact that in order to instate women into the received picture, that picture has to change. In this lecture, Sarah Hutton explores the ways in which attention has been refocused on the intellectual history of women over the past 25 years, and highlights in particular the work of recovery that has been necessary in the course of this research.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-03-sarah-hutton.mp3" length="12267544" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-03-sarah-hutton.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 3 Mar 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>48:46</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Otto of Freising and Historical Knowledge</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor David Luscombe (Sheffield) discusses the historical method in Otto of Freising's works of history</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Otto of Freising, uncle of Emperor Frederick of Barbarossa, belonged to the highest circles of German nobility, but he was also one of the most philosophical historians of the Middle Ages. In this lecture, David Luscombe discusses the historical method in Otto of Freising's two works of history, his Chronicle or History of the Two Cities (written between 1143 and 1147), and his Deeds of Emperor Frederick (written between 1156 and 1158).</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-01-david-luscombe.mp3" length="13290826" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2015-01-david-luscombe.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 3 Feb 2015 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>53:02</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>China and the European Enlightenment</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor S.J. Brown (Edinburgh) explores the rich scholarship of China and the European Enlightenment</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Vital themes in Europe's Enlightenment project included a new cosmopolitanism rooted in a growing awareness of other world cultures, an interest in forms of natural religion, and efforts to find a new foundation for social ethics apart from the moral laws and teachings of Christianity. In this lecture, S.J. Brown argues that Europe's growing awareness of China, and especially of Confucian thought, played a significant role in shaping the early European Enlightenment</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-13-s.j-brown.mp3" length="12881730" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-13-s.j-brown.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 2 Dec 2014 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>51:20</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Sporting St Patrick's Breastplate: war and peace in Irish Intellectual History</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Norman Vance (Sussex) discusses the importance of the hymn 'The Breastplate of St Patrick' to the understanding of early-modern and modern Irish intellectual history</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>In this wonderfully rich talk, Norman Vance explains how three interpretations of the Irish hymn 'The Breastplate of St Patrick', from Catholic, Episcopalian, and Presbyterian perspectives, are a pathway to studying the wider context of Irish intellectual history, taking in aspects of literary history, musicology, and theology.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-12-norman-vance.mp3" length="14136146" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-12-norman-vance.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2014 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>56:33</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Lost or Found in Translation? Varieties of Political Economy in the Enlightenment</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Tim Hochstrasser (LSE) delivers the second István Hont Memorial Lecture, examining how key aspects of political economic doctrines were transferred between countries during the Enlightenment</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>One of the themes of recent historiography in Enlightenment Studies focuses on how political economy gathers up so many of the key themes of the philosophers and reformers of the age into a discourse that crosses boundaries, national, institutional and linguistic. In this lecture Tim Hochstrasser examines this notion critically and re-assesses the claim that political economy is the defining and unifying discourse of the European Enlightenment. Brief case studies illustrate the intellectual transfer of key aspects of political economic doctrines between countries within Europe and beyond, including Latin America and India.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-11-tim-hochstrasser.mp3" length="10420638" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-11-tim-hochstrasser.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2014 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>41:04</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Rise of Mechanism: What and Why?</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor John Milton (KCL) examines the rise in importance of corpuscularianism in the context of the late seventeenth century</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>At the end of the seventeenth century, corpuscularianism, the mechanical philosophy, and mechanics (as a branch of applied mathematics) were all rising in importance. In this paper, John Milton provides a definitive account of these three concepts, how they relate to each other, and explains why they became popular.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-10-john-milton.mp3" length="12984184" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-10-john-milton.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 4 Nov 2014 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>55:13</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The City and the Soul in James Harrington's Republicanism</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Rachel Foxley (Reading) discusses how James Harrington used the maxims and terminology of the ancient world in his blueprint for a republican government</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>The political theorist James Harrington transformed and deployed many aspects of ancient thinking about the ethical character of the state in his political thought. In this paper, Rachel Foxley analyses Harrington's use of the correspondence between the city and the soul, arguing that this is a crucial mechanism enabling Harrington to attribute virtue to his ideal polity.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-09-rachel-foxley.mp3" length="12984184" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-09-rachel-foxley.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2014 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>51:45</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Political Economy and Utopia, or the Paternalistic Enlightenment in Scotland</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Knud Haakonssen (Erfurt and St Andrews) discusses the political theory hidden in Thomas Reid's lectures on politics</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Thomas Reid, the philosopher and founder of the Scottish School of Common Sense, did not publish much on politics, but his manuscripts reveal that he was deeply concerned with social, political and economic issues throughout his career. In this talk, Knud Haakonssen presents an analysis of Reid's hitherto unpublished Glasgow lecture notes, and shows that Reid was an acute commentator on contemporary politics and that his theoretical ideas framed solutions to some of the practical political and economic problems of his day.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-08-knud-haakonssen.mp3" length="13854755" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-08-knud-haakonssen.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 7 Oct 2014 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>55:23</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Exile from Exile: The Political Theory of Judith N. Shklar</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Andreas Hess (University College Dublin) presents an intellectual portrait of the political theorist Judith N. Shklar based on his recent biography</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>How has the concept of exile permeated the life and work of the political theorist Judith N. Shklar? In this talk, Andreas Hess discusses the subject of his recent book 'Exile from Exile'.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-07-andreas-hess.mp3" length="13361229" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-07-andreas-hess.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 17:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>53:20</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Referees, Editors, and Printers in the Making of Scientific Knowledge</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Aileen Fyfe (St Andrews) discusses the history of making and communicating scientific knowledge in the course of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Why is journal publication so important in the history of science, and how are they responsible for the making of scientific knowledge? In this lecture, Aileen Fyfe reveals the story behind the pages of the oldest scientific journal in existence, the Philosophic Transactions of the Royal Society.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-06-aileen-fyfe.mp3" length="12779764" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-06-aileen-fyfe.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2014 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>50:54</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Mill, Malthus and Class: Family Values and the Harm Principle</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Greg Claeys (Royal Holloway) delivers the inaugural István Hont Memorial Lecture, and explores an overlooked aspect of J.S. Mill's famous harm principle from On Liberty</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>So much has been written about the harm principle central to John Stuart Mill's classic work On Liberty that any attempt to supplement seems superfluous. However, an anomaly in accounts of one aspect of the text requires rectifying. In this lecture, Greg Claeys emphasises the Malthusian context of Mill's treatment of marriage, and argues that in On Liberty Mill regards the family, not the individual, as the foundational unit in society, and the right to bear children as conditional upon the  recognition of the basic duty to maintain them. His Malthusian proposal to restrict this right is the strongest instance of his application of paternalism to adults in a civilised society, but is in Mill's view entirely commensurate with the principle of liberty.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-05-greg-claeys.mp3" length="12124469" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-05-greg-claeys.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 6 May 2014 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>48:10</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Political Economy of Empire</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Donald Winch (St Andrews and Sussex) traces the development of the political economy of empire in the ideas of eighteenth- and nineteenth-century French and British economists</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Historians of economics have always been attracted to the political economy of empire because it tells us so much about how serious economic thinking has been shaped by colonial themes. In this lecture, Donald Winch explores this importance of colonies, arguing that whilst the political economy of empire was eventually a theory of capitalist imperialism, it still owed a great deal to those who formulated a case for colonisation as a remedy to some of Britain's problems as a mature economy in the 1820s and 1830s.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-02-donald-winch.mp3" length="14712721" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-02-donald-winch.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 4 Feb 2014 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>58:58</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Sociability between Natural Law and Sacred History, 1650-1800</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor John Robertson (Cambridge) delivers the inaugural lecture of the Institute of Intellectual History at the University of St Andrews</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>In this inaugural lecture of the Institute of Intellectual History at the University of St Andrews, Professor John Robertson asks how we can explain the concentration of interest, among the moral and political philosophers and historians of the Enlightenment, in the study of the formation and development of societies.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-01-john-robertson.mp3" length="14688271" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2014-01-john-robertson.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2014 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>58:51</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Every Great Revolution is a Civil War</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor David Armitage (Harvard) challenges the eighteenth-century narrative which separated the concepts of "civil war" and "revolution"</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>According to Reinhart Koselleck, the eighteenth century witnessed the gradual and permanent separation of concepts of "civil war" and "revolution". Placing these ideas in a longer perspective – a longue durée that goes back to republican Rome and comes forward to our own times – challenges this narrative by showing that civil war was the genus of which revolution was only a species. This argument presented by David Armitage can help us to rethink the late eighteenth-century "Age of Revolutions"; it can also explain the confusion as we attempt to understand political violence in places like Egypt and Syria today.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2013-05-david-armitage.mp3" length="26377081" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2013-05-david-armitage.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2013 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>53:26</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Trials of Douglas Young: Hitler, Aristophanes and the SNP</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Colin Kidd (St Andrews) delivers the third John Burrow Memorial Lecture, examining the Scottish nationalist response to the events of the 1940s</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>2013 sees the centenary of the birth of Douglas Young, one of the most influential figures in twentieth-century Scottish nationalism. Leader of the SNP from 1942 to the end of the Second World War, Young was imprisoned twice for refusing conscription – both military and industrial. He was also an eminent classicist, who translated some of the plays of Aristophanes into Lallans (Lowland Scots). In this lecture, Colin Kidd investigates Young's chequered career, and examine the broader context of the curious Scottish nationalist response to the world crisis of the 1940s.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2013-04-colin-kidd.mp3" length="30872686" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2013-04-colin-kidd.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>1:02:48</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>On Historical Distance</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Mark Salber Phillips (Carleton) develops ideas of historical distance, illustrating them with some examples of historical practice in 18th and 19th century Britain</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Ideas of historical distance have long been fundamental to Western conceptions of historical knowledge. In practice, however, distance seems to have dwindled into little more than a professional shibboleth - a way of defending the historian's labours against the simplifications of popular journalism or the shortcuts of the guided tour. In common usage, historical distance refers to a position of detached observation made possible by the passage of time, but the standard conception narrows the idea of distance and burdens it with a regulatory purpose. In this lecture, Mark Salber Philips  argues that distance needs to be re-conceived in terms of the wider set of engagements that mediate our relations to the past, as well as the full spectrum of distance-positions from near to far. Re-imagined in these terms, distance sheds its prescriptiveness and becomes a valuable heuristic for examining the range and variability of historical representation.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2013-03-mark-salber-phillips.mp3" length="25980897" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2013-03-mark-salber-phillips.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>52:36</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Democracy and Empire</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Richard Whatmore (Sussex) considers the first descriptions of democracy in the Enlightenment era and how we continue to define what it means today</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>One of the great surprises of modern thought is the survival of democracy. Today the victory of democracy continues to be associated with the American and French Revolutions. But democracy was for the most part castigated by reformers and revolutionaries across Europe during the enlightenment era. Attempts to apply democratic ideas universally were generally ridiculed. In this lecture, Richard Whatmore argues that the challenge faced by advocates of democracy was to make the theory compatible with larger forms of state; in short, to turn a democracy into a stable empire.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2013-02-richard-whatmore.mp3" length="25670556" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2013-02-richard-whatmore.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 5 Mar 2013 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>51:57</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Two 17th Century Century Concepts of Liberty and their Legacy</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Blair Worden (Oxford) discusses the two 17th century concepts of religious and civil liberty and their legacy</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Over the quarter of a millennium from the later seventeenth century to the Great War, the phrase 'civil and religious liberty' was a pervasive feature of English political language. How and why had the phrase come into being? In 1600 it would have been unintelligible. The alliance of religious with civil liberty became possible only when religious liberty acquired a new meaning and became something like a human right. In this lecture, Blair Worden argues that its emergence has two claims on our attention. It betokened a new conception of the relationship between God and society. And it demonstrates the capacity of political events, and of pressures of political power, to shape developments in intellectual history.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2013-01-blair-worden.mp3" length="25314467" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2013-01-blair-worden.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2013 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>51:13</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Mythos, Ethos, and Pathos of the Humanities</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Ian Hunter (Queensland) discusses the effects of theory on the humanities in Australia</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Justifications of the humanities often employ a mythos that exceeds their historical dispositions and reach. This applies to justifications that appeal to an 'idea' of the humanities grounded in the cultivation of reason for its own sake. But the same problem affects more recent accounts that seek to shatter this idea by admitting an 'event' capable of dissolving and refounding the humanities in 'being'. In offering a sketch of the emergence of the modern humanities from early modern humanism, the paper argues that these twin philosophical justifications fail to capture both the array of intellectual arts that have informed the humanities disciplines and the variety of uses to which these arts have been put. Nonetheless, the two philosophical constructions have had a concrete impact on the disposition of the modern humanities, seen in the respective structuralist and poststructuralist reconfigurations of the disciplines that began to take place under the banner of 'theory' during the 1960s. In discussing the effects of theory on the humanities in Australia, Ian Hunter focuses on the unforseeable consequences of attempts to provide arts-based disciplines with a foundation either in cognitive structures or in an 'event' that shatters them.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-08-ian-hunter.mp3" length="20997742" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-08-ian-hunter.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2012 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>42:13</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Calvinists, Socinians and Arminians: Reformation and natural rights in early modern political thought</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor James Moore (Concordia University) examines three denominations of Protestant theology in their early modern political context</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>In this lecture, James Moore discusses three denominations of Protestant theology: Calvinism, or the dogmatic theology of the Reformed or Presbyterian churches; the theology of the Arminians or the Remonstrants in the Netherlands, the most important of whom for the purposes of this lecture is Hugo Grotius; and the theology of the Socinians, the most significant of whom was John Locke. It is a story that travels from Geneva to Holland, to England, and back to Geneva for some closing remarks on Jean-Jacques Rousseau, whose political principles are taken to be a return to the principles of Calvin and his followers.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-09-james-moore.mp3" length="22979277" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-09-james-moore.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2012 15:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>46:21</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Benjamin Franklin's Radical Agrarian Project</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Manuela Albertone (University of Turin) explains Franklin's interest in radical political and economic reform in Britain and in France</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Benjamin Franklin's interest in physiocracy and the radical implications of French economic ideas extended from Turgot and Condorcet to the British radical milieus. In this lecture, Manuela Albertone highlights Franklin's ability to deliver economic reflection and radical thought, and his passionate belief that only a new attention to the nature of land ownership and its role could combat the forces of corruption so prevalent in commercial societies and shape a modern republic.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-07-manuela-albertone.mp3" length="29992485" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-07-manuela-albertone.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>58:52</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Karl Marx: 'Ricardian Socialist'?</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Dr Keith Tribe (Sussex) considers whether the label 'Ricardian Socialist' is applicable to Karl Marx</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>With the general loss of interest in  Marx as an analyst of capitalism, argument over the development of his thinking, from his early writings to Capital Vol. I, has given way to a more or less uncritical acceptance of Capital as the centrepiece of his endeavours, and a neglect of its sources. However, in 1913 Lenin rightly noted that there were "three sources and component parts" of "Marxism": German philosophy, English political economy, and French socialism. Curiously, few readers of Marx have taken this point seriously; while some attention has been paid to "German philosophy", little attention has been paid to the importance of Proudhon and others, while almost none at all has ever been paid to Marx's debt to the writings of David Ricardo and Adam Smith. In this lecture, Keith Tribe seeks to readdress this imbalance in Marx scholarship.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-06-keith-tribe.mp3" length="31165241" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-06-keith-tribe.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 9 May 2012 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>01:03:24</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Arnold Toynbee's Industrial Revolution</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Donald Winch (Sussex) on the intelletual legacy of Arnold Toynbee's Industrial Revolution</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Arnold Toynbee's Oxford lectures on the 'Industrial Revolution' were once thought to have been responsible for coining and diffusing an idea that has remained essential to students of British history since the lectures were posthumously published in 1882. Toynbee has also been credited with transmitting an interpretation of the revolution that became known, in the words of E. P. Thompson, as 'classical catastrophic orthodoxy'. In this lecture, Donald Winch re-examines Toynbee's role as historian of catastrophe and his remedies for dealing with its consequences with the aim of establishing the nineteenth-century political, moral, and intellectual context within which his interpretation of the industrial revolution can best be understood.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-05-donald-winch.mp3" length="24407110" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-05-donald-winch.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2012 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>49:19</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Travels with Alexis de Tocqueville</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Jeremy Jennings (QMUL) on Alexis de Tocqueville's Democracy in America</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>'Demoracy in America' by Alexis de Tocqueville is possibly the most famous book about America, but what did Tocqueville see when he visited America and how did his visit influence his writing? In this lecture, Jeremy Jennings seeks to answer both of these questions and to cast light on how other French authors saw America in the nineteenth century.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-04-jeremy-jennings.mp3" length="32822148" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-04-jeremy-jennings.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2012 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>1:02:52</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The sociological imagination in mid-twentieth century Britain and America</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Peter Mandler (Cambridge) on the language of social science in everyday discourse</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>How has the language of social science penetrated its way into the everyday discourse of educated people, particularly in the period after the Second World War? In this lecture, Peter Mandler examines the extent to which people in mid-twentieth century Britain and America used the conceptual tools of psychology, sociology and anthropology to view their personal 'issues' also as social 'problems'.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-03-peter-mandler.mp3" length="29679754" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-03-peter-mandler.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2012 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>56:20</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Reading Rousseau in Latin America</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Nicola Miller (UCL) on the reception of Jean-Jacques Rousseau in Latin America</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>It is well known that many of the leaders of the Wars of Independence invoked Rousseau in support of their challenge to colonial authority, but how exactly were Rousseau's works read and interpreted in early nineteenth-century Latin America? In this lecture, Nicola Miller identifies variations in how Rousseau's ideas were adopted and adapted by different actors, in different parts of the region, in order to explore the problems and possibilities of explaining how and why ideas travel.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-02-nicola-miller.mp3" length="26546488" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-02-nicola-miller.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>49:48</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>What gave you that idea Paddy?</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Norman Vance (Sussex) on genealogies of the Irish mind</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Is there such a thing as 'the Irish mind', or is that the ultimate Irish joke? If there is a distinctive Irish intellectual history, how did it develop in the face of the disruptions of a complicated and traumatic political and social history? Somehow, new ideas and initiatives keep bubbling up in every generation, but where do they come from? Is there an Irish intellectual aristocracy, or should that be aristocracies? In this lecture, Norman Vance explores these and other Irish questions.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-01-norman-vance.mp3" length="26649702" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2012-01-norman-vance.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 6 Feb 2012 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>50:01</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The very idea of the University</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Stefan Collini (Cambridge) delivers the second annual John Burrow Memorial Lecture</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Stefan Collini offers a few brief reflections on the history and current state of the institution we call the university, and then goes on to propose a vocabulary and a perspective which enable us to discuss the role of such institutions in more fruitful terms than the clichés about 'contributing to economic growth' which currently dominate public debate on the topic. This lecture was given in memory of John Wyon Burrow (1935-2009), who was the first holder of a chair in Intellectual History at the University of Sussex and was one of the founder members of the subject at this university.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2011-04-stefan-collini.mp3" length="26426730" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2011-04-stefan-collini.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 5 Dec 2011 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>49:33</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Pilgrim's Progress in the Evangelical Revival</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Isabel Rivers (QMUL) on the reception of John Bunyan's Pilgrim's Progress in the eighteenth century</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>First published in two parts in 1678 and 1683, 'Pilgrim's Progress' was to become the most popular religious work in English after the King James Bible. In this lecture, Isabel Rivers explores its fortunes in the evangelical revival of the eighteenth century: how it was made into a polemical text in the battles between Arminians and Calvinists; how it was used for pastoral purposes, both in print and in society meetings; and how it became a means of writing the history of dissent and evangelicalism.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2011-03-isabel-rivers.mp3" length="38083595" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2011-03-isabel-rivers.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2011 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>1:13:50</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Sacred History and Political Thought 1650-1750</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor John Robertson (Cambridge) on Neapolitan historians Giambattista Vico and Pietro Giannone</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>How was the Hobbesian proposition - that man was not naturally sociable - answered by recourse to sacred history, the account of the ancient Hebrews and contemporary peoples found in the Old Testament? Focussing particularly on the Neapolitan historians Giambattista Vico and Pietro Giannone, in this lecture John Robertson shows how they adapted and extended the framework for the study of sacred history laid down by the authorities in Rome, and from this, produced remarkably original accounts of the formation of society.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2011-02-john-robertson.mp3" length="33512155" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2011-02-john-robertson.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2011 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>1:04:19</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>John Maynard Keynes: Economist as Biographer and Intellectual Historian</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor Donald Winch (Sussex) examines Keynes's work devoted to biographical studies and psychological character analysis</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>Biography was an occupation which sustained Keynes throughout his life in parallel with his work as an economist, and it resulted in his 'Essays in Biography', first published in 1933 but expanded by later essays that make up the Royal Economic Society (RES) edition of this work. As Publications Secretary to the RES, Donald Winch has written a reappraisal of Keynes's work in this field to accompany a reissue of the essays. The lecture is based on this and deals with the literary context of Keynes's essays, showing their Bloomsbury roots and their origin in such fields as genealogy, eugenics, Freudian psychoanalysis, and Keynes's need to understand the intellectual traditions that had conditioned economics as a policy-oriented discipline – the discipline to which Keynes was to make a major contribution in his 'General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money' in 1936.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2011-01-donald-winch.mp3" length="30000566" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2011-01-donald-winch.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 6 Jun 2011 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>57:00</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
<title>Anglican Enlightenment and Christian revelation: The reception of Gibbon's Decline and Fall</title>
<itunes:subtitle>Professor J.G.A. Pocock (Johns Hopkins) discusses two chapters of Gibbon's Decline and Fall on the spread of Christianity</itunes:subtitle>
<itunes:summary>In 1776, two chapters of Edward Gibbon's 'Decline and Fall' on the spread of Christianity were published. They aroused such controversy that it is still supposed that Gibbon wrote his history as an attack on religion. In this lecture, Professor Pocock argues to the contrary that the two chapters were prematurely written, and that the controversy is to be understood in the setting of the Church of England's need to reconcile a civil religion with the belief in Christian revelation.</itunes:summary>
<itunes:image href="https://www.intellectualhistory.net/assets/images/podcast.jpg" />
<enclosure url="https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2010-01-j.g.a-pocock.mp3" length="28042030" type="audio/mpeg" />
<guid>https://traffic.libsyn.com/intellectualhistory/2010-01-j.g.a-pocock.mp3</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 2 Mar 2010 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<itunes:duration>52:55</itunes:duration>
<itunes:keywords></itunes:keywords>
<itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
